[Music]
after that
introduction chapter one so to
speak I'd like to introduce you to the
catalog of the most important manifolds
what do we mean by a manifold well a
manifold is a generalization of Curves
and surfaces to other three
dimensions that's how any course
starts so at definition but it's not
quite a definition
a
manifold and I'm going to abbreviate it
as
MFD is a
nice
[Music]
smooth geometric
[Applause]
figure that
generalizes curves and surfaces as I say
to arbitrary
Dimensions so we all know what curves
and surfaces look like and if you think
of higher dimensional versions that's
manif dim is always
Dimensions the official definition if
you want a definition in terms of terms
that go back to set theory is long and
complicated
official
definition is long and
Technical but this idea is enough for us
to use what manifolds are and what they
are good
for instead of defining it we shall see
what they really are it's like saying
how do you define
say s African cuisine well you can have
you know 10 volumes of philosophical
discourse on how to define South African
cuisine but it's better to taste maybe
10 typical dishes and then you
understand what South African cuisine is
like and besides you should understand
that definitions were created by
people yeah they had lots and lots of
examples that they wanted to organize
and they invented a definition not the
other way around if you're learning
mathematics as a student you might think
definition was given To Us by God but he
wasn't we have if you are developed in
mathematics if researchers we have lots
of lots of different situations and we
want to organize them into something
simple and that's when we introduce the
definition so let's see some examples
topologically manifolds can
be
buildt from
the following simple
ingredients basic building blocks of
manifolds and then I'll discuss some
interesting manifolds but first basing
basic building
BLS in order to build the manifolds I
need first and foremost what we shall
called an N dimensional ball or n
ball for sure
what do I mean by this our notation for
this there is no really standard
notation but it will be b superscript n
on the on the upper shoulder and this is
simply equal to the set of
points in an nend
dimensional real space if you like such
that the
sum of the squares is less than equal to
one okay less than or equal to not equal
to not not strictly rest
than let's draw some pictures so this is
dimension and n and this is B of
n when n is one what do you think it
is well we just follow this definition r
to one that's a straight
line and yes you were saying sorry
somebody said something what do you
think it
is yeah so it's the path which is
between Min -1 and + one and it's this
part at distance at most one away from
the origin so that's it doesn't look
like a ball but it is it's called a one
ball ball of Dimension One some people
call it the unit ball of Dimension One
Two it's the boundary and inside of the
dis of radius
one okay from the origin and that's the
one ball although it doesn't look like a
ball it's the ball Dimension one
dimension two and three that's the most
familiar
case you get the picture looks quite
similar to the previous one but if you
see what I mean that's what what it's
going to look
like all the points that are within
distance one or equal to distance one
from the origin and that's the standard
ball
now this is the B but we shall introduce
some other terminology we shall say that
this is the disk instead of a ball so
when we say a dis we mean this s that
makes sense also we'll introduce another
term which is 01
will be called I always and it's called
Unit
interval because this term is so common
that it's useful to have it at our
disposal okay so far we have defined um
lots of different
terms notice that this 01 unit interval
is half of the one
B
okay second
ingredient we want spheres in addition
to boths so nus one
sphere what do we mean by nus one sphere
here the notation is completely standard
I'm not inventing this it's s to n minus
one again in the exponent position and
this is the boundary of that object
namely it's the collection of all the
points in RN again such that the sum of
the
squares is exactly equal to one and
those are are called spheres the
previous ones are called
balls so let's look at a list of
various in various Dimensions SN minus
one notice that I'm looking at n here 01
two and 1 2 3 and so on but here I have
SN minus
one what
is then the object we get for Nal 1 that
is we have to ask what is s0 Zero
Dimensional sphere well according to
this it's easy you draw the real AIS and
then collect all the points that are
exactly at distance one from the origin
you agree so that's simply equal to how
many points are
there exactly there exactly two points
at distance one from the
origin so this is the Zero Dimensional
sphere it doesn't look like a sphere but
it
is dimension two that's
easy it's this object at distance one
from the
origin and please note that this is also
known as a
circle I open terminological
parenthesis all of science has been
plagued by the confusion about what we
being mean by Circle sphere disc and the
ball if you listen to physicist they
always say oh let's take a circle and
they have to say oh I mean the inside of
the circle also or just the boundary of
the circle blah blah blah blah blah blah
blah well mathematicians at least
educated mathematicians resolve this
terminological problem a century ago
when they say a circle they mean only
the curve which is the boundary of the
disc and when they mean that they never
an educated mathematician never calls it
Circle they call it a dis well an
educated mathematician might call it a
circle if the mathematician is talking
to ignorant
physic in
return in return those ignorant
physicists might teach a thing or two to
mathematicians but anyway this
terminological distinction can be made
at no extra cost to any real science so
we should stick to it so that's a this
that's a cirle and dimension three
that's easy that's the most familiar one
this is
called a two sphere so note that this
picture please understand that this is a
is a Surface you might think that this
is just a yellow line on the Blackboard
but it isn't a yellow line on the
Blackboard it's a surface and it is what
you call sometimes a spherical
shell yeah this surface I don't include
what's inside
that's included in the three ble two
sphere is just a spherical
shell sometimes physicist and Engineers
call this solid sphere but we shall
always call it the
three so those are the examples and they
are all familiar and note that only in
dimension zero the sphere is
disconnected okay
now we shall
introduce a very useful
symbol and we are not going to worry too
much about what this symbol means
symbols
first you might have seen
this this C there you must have seen
this in the context of partial
derivative but for us it would mean
boundary of
something
okay a few
examples boundary
of how do you pronounce this
symbol Nall yeah is equal to nus one
here in particular the boundary operator
because it's an operation
drops the dimension by one boundary of
something n dimensional is n minus one
dimensional similarly boundary of the
untwisted ordinary strip that we played
with
yesterday what is
that it's equal
to this circle
above and this Circle B so it's a
disjoint Union of two circles
okay have
[Music]
to why am I not defining
SN well what's the difference for
example
S4 well that's okay S4 can be thought of
as S5 -1 or S4 but it's more convenient
because I wanted to have this emphasis
it's purely pedagogical if you're
confused don't worry about this I mean 1
2 three but these are dimensions zero 1
two and so because I wanted to put balls
and spheres next to each other that's
that's
right you don't have to worry about it
you are not confused it's just that my
sort of pedagogical trick did not agree
with you but there's no
has a meaning so why do you have to no
but it doesn't matter this is a dummy
variable it doesn't matter what I call
it I mean I could have called it s of
for
example something like
this it doesn't matter this can be
any it means dimension in
Chinese but it doesn't matter what you
call it in practice you have S
S8 and if you see S8 you have to
remember that it is the unit sphere
in our R is the unit sphere in what R
not R7
R9 S8 is unit sphere in
R9 S2 is the unit sphere in R3 S1 is the
unit circle in R2 and so on you see why
it's pedagogically helpful to think of n
minus one this is one dimensional low
than the ambient I menion okay but it
does it doesn't really matter any other
questions
okay let's now take the mov
strip you remember these
animals what is the boundary of this
this manifold it's not a very good
picture excuse
me like this what's the boundary of this
man
huh so let's see where the bandary is
that means that I take my finger on the
edge and start tracing the edge okay in
the ordinary case if I trace this Edge I
come back after one turn and the bottom
still has to be traced separately that's
why there are two components to the band
in the case of mov Street power if I
trace my finger on this Edge whoop I
come
downstairs and then I come here and then
I keep tracing it and then finally I
come back to where I
started so this thing is exactly it is a
single
Circle which looks like
this which is the same thing as a single
ccle
I shall explain what this symbol means
in the moment but it is a single Circle
it looks complicated but it is a single
CLE yeah the difference between a mish
strip and an
ordinary um strip is that the boundary
is one
copy of S1 for the ordinary strip and
two copies sorry two copies of this one
for the
ordering strip and one
copy of S1 for the movie strip okay all
that is linguistic exercise I'm teaching
you mathematical English more than
anything
else okay and now I'm going to
do a final
thing another very useful symbol after
the B symbol is this
symbol this symbol will mean
homeomorphic
to it's not
standard if you have learned in your
previous life what homeomorphic means so
much the better welcome to the club if
you have never learned what homeomorphic
means don't worry it simply means
topologically the same
as now of course topologically the same
as is not not a very precise way of
expressing oneself but that's okay what
you think it is is almost certainly what
it is so don't worry when problem arises
I'll correct
you our approach is to rely on people's
reasonable intuition and to develop that
intuition rather than spend most of the
course defining things leaving no time
for
applications Okay so some
examples B1 is topologically the same as
I do you remember those
symbols
yeah and
also if you have something like
this this is topologically same as S1
okay and
the these building
blocks I have defined only two kinds of
building blocks essentially balls and
spheres some of the balls have
traditional names diss some of the
Spheres have traditional names
circles but those building blocks
generate all the other manifolds in
fact complicated and interesting
[Applause]
manuls that we shall encounter
interesting and useful
manifes via you combine them operations
of
product you can multiply
manifolds
quotient you can divide
manifolds and finally something called
connected sum or
surgery and this is a little like adding
and subtracting manif cut and paste
and these operations product quotient
and surgery how to multiply divide and
add and subtract manles will be the
theme of tomorrow's lecture